Guide to the New Day Films Archive, 1969-2018 RL.10180
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- New Day Films Cooperative Files, 1981-2012; 14.5 Linear Feet 29 boxes
  - Cooperative Files: Meetings, 1981-2001; 3.7 Linear Feet 7.5 boxes
    Files typically contain a mix of agendas; minutes; notes, usually written up by the consultant Arlene Goldbard; reports from committees and individuals; correspondence to the Committee or between members; financial summaries and analyses; membership tasks; and the annual "State of the Co-op" reports. Topics covered by the materials cover all aspects of New Day Film's operations and mission. Corollary materials for meetings and topical content are often found in other administrative series in the same calendar periods.
    Materials in this series are closed to use until 2025.
    - Centralization Committee report and notes, 1981 May-June (Box 32)
    - Steering Committee meeting notes and minutes, 1981 December (Box 32)
    - Steering Committee conference calls, 1982 (Box 32)
    - Steering Committee meeting notes and minutes, 1982 November (Box 32)
    - Steering Committee conference calls, 1983 (Box 32)
    - Annual meeting agenda and minutes, 1983 June (Box 32)
    - Steering Committee meeting minutes and correspondence to Steering Committee, 1983 February-November (Box 32)
    - Steering Committee conference calls and letter about computer issues, 1984 January-May (Box 32)
    - Annual meeting agenda and minutes, 1984 June (Box 32)
    - Meetings timeline and summaries, 1984 (Box 32)
      Pages of handwritten notes provide a list of all New Day Films meeting dates from May 1981 to March 1984, with a brief paragraph stating topics and issues discussed. Probably compiled to support the momentous 1984 administrative transition.
    - Annual Steering Committee and Member Meeting agendas and minutes, 1985 June; 3 folders (Box 32)
    - Steering Committee meeting agenda and minutes, 1985 November (Box 32)
    - Preliminary Steering Committee meeting agendas, 1985-1986 (Box 32)
    - Agenda planning notes for 1986 annual meeting, Spring 1986 (Oversize-folder 1)
      On two very large sheets that were posted on the wall.
    - Steering Committee conference calls, Annual Meeting, and other meeting agendas and minutes, 1986 January-November; 6 folders (Box 32)
    - Steering Committee conference calls, Annual Meeting, and other meeting agendas and minutes, 1987 January-November; 11 folders (Box 33)
    - Steering Committee conference calls, Annual Meeting, and other meeting agendas and minutes, 1988 February-October; 9 folders (Box 33)
    - Steering Committee conference calls, Annual Meeting, and other meeting agendas and minutes, 1989 January-November; 12 folders (Box 34)
    - Steering Committee conference calls, Annual Meeting, and other meeting agendas and minutes, 1990 April-December; 6 folders (Box 34)
    - Steering Committee conference calls, Annual Meeting, and other meeting agendas and minutes, 1991 March-November; 9 folders (Box 35)
    - Steering Committee conference calls, Annual Meeting, and other meeting agendas and minutes, 1992 January-November; 9 folders (Box 35)
    - Steering Committee conference calls, Annual Meeting, and other meeting agendas and minutes, 1993 June-November; 7 folders (Box 35)
    - Steering Committee conference calls, Annual Meeting, and other meeting agendas and minutes, 1994 January-November; 5 folders (Box 36)
    - Steering Committee conference calls, Annual Meeting, and other meeting agendas and minutes, 1995 June-November; 5 folders (Box 36)
    - Steering Committee conference calls, Annual Meeting, and other meeting agendas and minutes, 1996 January-November; 13 folders (Box 36)
    - Steering Committee conference calls, Annual Meeting, and other meeting agendas and minutes, 1997 January-November; 11 folders (Box 37)
    - Steering Committee conference calls, Annual Meeting, and other meeting agendas and minutes, 1998 January-June; 6 folders (Box 37)
    - Steering Committee conference calls, Annual Meeting, and other meeting agendas and minutes, 1998 August-December; 5 folders (Box 38)
    - Steering Committee conference calls, Annual Meeting, and other meeting agendas and minutes, 1999 January-December; 8 folders (Box 38)
    - Steering Committee conference calls, Annual Meeting, and other meeting agendas and minutes, 2000 February-October; 7 folders (Box 38)
    - Steering Committee conference calls, Annual Meeting, and other meeting agendas and minutes, 2000 November; 2 folders (Box 39)
    - Steering Committee conference calls, Annual Meeting, and other meeting agendas and minutes, 2001 January-June; 4 folders (Box 39)
  - Cooperative Files: Core Operations Chronological Files, 1983-1994; .6 Linear Feet 1 box
    This sequence of files, preserved in its original order as maintained by and for the New Day Films cooperative facilitators Arlene Goldbard and Don Adams hired around 1984, were originally titled "Core Ops Chron Files." It begins with a folder with New Day Films' 1983 articles of incorporation, then continues with folders of mixed materials relating to New Day operations: meeting and conference call notes, reports, personnel matters, policies and planning, and related correspondence. Some of the meeting materials overlap with items in the previous series and materials in later files.
    - New Day Films Articles of Incorporation, copy sent to facilitators, 1983 January (Box 39)
      Incorporated in California. Gives names and addresses of 1983 directors, all living in Berkeley.
    - Meeting notes, reports, and correspondence, 1985 June-September (Box 39)
    - Meeting notes, reports, and correspondence, 1985-1986 (Box 39)
    - Planning timeline from November 1986 to June 1987, printed (Box 65)
      Stamped in red ink, right corner December 1987; this usually indicates when the facilitator received the item.
    - Meeting notes, reports, and correspondence, 1987 June-November (Box 39)
    - Meeting notes, reports, and correspondence, 1988 January-May (Box 39)
    - Meeting notes, reports, and correspondence, 1988 September-October (Box 39)
    - Meeting notes, reports, and correspondence, 1989 February-June (Box 39)
    - Meeting notes, reports, and correspondence, 1990 June-1992 May; 4 folders (Box 39)
    - Meeting notes, reports, and correspondence, 1992-1994 (Box 39)
  - Cooperative Files: Facilitators Correspondence, 1986-2001; 1.5 Linear Feet 3 boxes
    This sequence of files, preserved in its original order as maintained by and for the New Day facilitators Goldbard and Adams, consists almost wholly of email printouts, arranged chronologically, with only a few attachments and other materials. These emails cover almost every aspect of administrative operations, in particular organizing the annual meetings, New Day publicity, films distribution, and membership issues.
    Other smaller groups of correspondence files are located in the Brandon and Rothschild series, and correspondence can be found embedded in many other files, especially in the facilitators' records.
    - Correspondence, 1995 June-October (Box 40)
    - Correspondence, 1995 October-1996 January (Box 40)
    - 25th anniversary correspondence, 1995-1996 (Box 40)
    - Correspondence, 1996 January-December; 4 folders (Box 40)
    - Correspondence, 1997 January-December; 5 folders (Box 41)
    - Correspondence, 1998 January-November; 3 folders (Box 41)
    - Meeting notes, reports, and correspondence, 1999 January-December; 2 folders (Box 42)
    - Meeting notes, reports, and correspondence, 2000 January-December; 2 folders (Box 42)
    - Correspondence, 2001 January-June (Box 42)
    - Correspondence files, Adams & Goldbard, 1986-1996; 3 folders (Box 42)
  - Cooperative Files: Topical, 1983-2012, bulk 1983-2001; 6.0 Linear Feet 12 boxes
    Going by markings on the papers, these files were likely maintained by the consultant firm but access may have been shared with cooperative members or Steering Committee. They are arranged in subgroups as originally titled: Activity Reports; Adams and Goldbard; Anniversaries; Central Office; Computers; Dubbing House; Executive Committee; Film Files; Finances; General Policies; Karol Media (distribution manager for New Day); Membership; Personnel; Operations; Outreach/Intake; Promotional (the largest group); Shipping; Tasks; and Website. Materials in this series overlap with other co-op files and to a lesser degree with the co-founder files.
    As is reflected by their titles, these file groups contain documents that are central to understanding the cooperative's core functions. Of special interest are folders with papers and articles concerning the lawsuits pursued by New Day Films, several of which were of importance to the independent film enterprise as a whole. Also of interest is a folder of photographs of New Day founders and members (1972-2011), and a copy of New Day's policy manual.
    Subgroup files are usually arranged in alphabetical order by folder title, but some, such as Finances, are arranged chronologically. Within folders, materials are generally in date order.
    - Activity reports, 1984 January-1997 April; 3 folders (Box 43)
    - Adams & Goldbard (facilitators), 1984-2001; 19 folders (Box 43)
      These files relate to the activities of the Adams and Goldbard consultancy firm, and chiefly contain contracts and agreements, invoices for services, feasibility reports, and other documents related to their role as facilitators for New Day Films. Files assembled and maintained by the facilitators make up roughly half of the New Day Films records, and document the full scope of their activities for New Day.
    - Anniversaries: screening event files, press kits, correspondence, 1983-1996; 6 folders (Box 43)
      These files include press kits, correspondence, and other materials related to New Day anniversary events at the Museum of Modern Art, and in Chicago, Juneau, and West Virginia.
    - Anniversaries: screening event files, press kits, clippings, correspondence, 1996-2012; 7 folders (Box 44)
      These files include press kits, correspondence, and other materials related to New Day 25th anniversary screenings in Massachusetts, San Francisco, New York, and at the Full Frame Documentary Festival.
    - Anniversaries: 25th anniversary mailing and publicity brochure, 1996 (Box 44)
      Large folder chiefly containing email printouts, and a printed piece to commemorate the anniversary.
    - Anniversaries: 25th anniversary blurb in 1998 issue of journal, Angles: Women Working in Film and Video, 6 folders (Box 44)
    - Central Office: reports, memos, correspondence, meeting notes, 1985-1990; 13 folders (Box 44)
      The Central Office was established to manage the cooperative's core operations. Topics in these papers include the computer system and database; booking procedures; personnel contracts, policies, and salaries; the transition to a new manager; end of year reports; and Steering Committee communications. An office space lease dated September 1989 has been moved to an oversize box.
    - Lease for office space in New York City, 1989 September (Box 64)
    - Computer files: Reports, cost estimates, correspondence, 1988-1998; 5 folders (Box 44)
    - Computer files: Reports, cost estimates, correspondence, 1998-2000; 3 folders (Box 45)
    - Dubbing House correspondence, 1995-2000; 4 folders (Box 45)
      Correspondence about the ups and downs of using various video duplication partners.
    - Executive Committee minutes, 1990-1992 (Box 45)
      Correspondence about various personnel, budget, and costs issues.
    - Film files: Film applications, 1989-1996; 2 folders (Box 45)
      Applications files document requests for new films, status changes, and the recruitment, screening, and selection process.
    - Film files: Booking activity and operations, 1987-1992 (Box 45)
    - Film files: Film clip reels, 1996 (Box 45)
    - Film files: Dubbing, 1996-1998 (Box 45)
    - Film files: Fulfillment, 1987-1993 (Box 45)
    - Film files: Letter with recommendations on video pricing, 1992 (Box 45)
    - Film files: Market profiles, 1988 January (Box 45)
    - Film files: National Film Market, 1986-1987 (Box 45)
    - Film files: New member recruitment, new films, 1990-1998 (Box 45)
    - Film files: Proposals, agreements, 1987-1994 (Box 45)
    - Film files: Status change, 1989-1997 (Box 45)
    - Finances: Pier 84, 1984 (Box 46)
    - Finances: 1986 Tax Reform Act as related to artists, 1986-1988 (Box 46)
    - Finances: Non-profits, 1986-1988 (Box 46)
    - Finances: Financial agreements and records, 1987 (Box 46)
    - Finances: 1987-1988 budget (Box 46)
    - Finances: Accounting, 1989 (Box 46)
    - Finances: Business plan, 1989 May (Box 46)
    - Finances: Budget reports, correspondence, meeting binder, and shares, 1989-1991; 5 folders (Box 46)
    - Finances: National Video Resources/Rockefeller Foundation grant, 1991 (Box 46)
    - Finances: Shares and grosses, 1992 (Box 46)
    - Finances: Booking and income report, 1992 (Box 46)
    - Finances: Spreadsheets, memos, reports, 1992-1993 (Box 46)
    - Finances: Futures, 1992-1994 (Box 46)
      Cluster of emails, notes, and reports pertaining to: a financial overhaul of New Day; video and nonprofit media market trends; membership survey questionnaire results; possible new partnerships with Film Arts Foundation; and proposed formation of New Day Educational Media non-profit arm.
    - Finances: Budget and activity reports, shares, and emails, 1993-1995; 4 folders (Box 46)
    - Finances: Budget and activity reports, shares, emails, and tasks, 1996-2001; 9 folders (Box 47)
    - General Policies, 1984-1991; 4 folders (Box 47)
      Files contain New Day's General Policies document, revised annually, governing New Day Films and its membership. Provides an in-depth look at New Day's organization, principles, membership responsibilities, and fiscal management. Annotated revisions often present, along with blank liability statements, memos, and other supporting materials. The 7-page 1984 document had grown by 1996 to 28 pages with a table of contents.
    - General Policies, 1992-2000; 5 folders (Box 48)
    - Karol Media: Reports, transition, requests for proposals, 1984-1987; 3 folders (Box 48)
      Karol Media was a distribution manager for New Day Films.
    - Lawsuits: New Day Films v. New Day Film, 1977-1979; 2 folders (Box 48)
      Includes court documents, correspondence, articles, and photocopies of ads by the defendants, who produced pornographic films. Also includes announcement of New Day Films cooperative's successful outcome.
    - Lawsuits: New Day Films v. Planned Parenthood of Schenectady (New Day Software division), 1987-1989; 2 folders (Box 49)
      Civil action against a software developer associated with Planned Parenthood of Schenectady, N.Y.
    - Membership: Member photographs, 1972-2011 (Box 49)
      Mostly black-and-white group photographs, including the co-founders in 1972 and 1973, the membership in 1973, and later group shots, one taken in 2011 (color). Also includes several contact sheets and strips.
    - Membership: Administrative files, 1986-1990s; 11 folders (Box 49)
      Folders contain correspondence, memos, and reports about New Day Films membership, including membership status requests, financial contributions, new member recruitment, and surveys on the future of the cooperative. A 1989 folder contains biographies and resumes of members.
    - Membership: Member lists, 1988-2000 and undated; 6 folders (Box 49)
    - New Day Educational Media (NDEA): Fundraising, correspondence, proposals, 1990-1991; 2 folders (Box 50)
    - Operations: Reports, 1985-1988 (Box 50)
    - Operations: Manual, 1989 April; 2 folders (Box 50)
    - Outreach/intake: Correspondence, 1997-2000; 6 folders (Box 50)
      Files consist almost wholly of email printouts concerning new member recruitment and other forms of outreach. Intake and outreach reports contain data on the source for request (website, referral, conference, ads), and minority recruitment. There are also documents concerning film submissions and new member names.
    - Outreach/intake: Correspondence, 2000-2001; 2 folders (Box 51)
    - Personnel, 1985-1990s; 6 folders (Box 51)
      Files comprise personnel reports, employment agreements, hiring, financial reporting, member biographies and resumes, new member recruitment, and a member survey. May contain potentially sensitive information; privacy laws apply.
    - Promotion: Publicity about New Day Films, 1974-1988 (Box 51)
      Primarily fliers advertising screenings or film sales; also includes a number of photocopied clippings and articles about the cooperative and its filmmakers.
    - Promotion: Early marketing and outreach, reports, and correspondence, 1985-1993 (Box 51)
    - Promotion: Reports and proposals, 1986-1989 (Box 51)
      Includes the 1986 report by Margaret Cooper, Comprehensive catalog: a review of current nontheatrical distributors' policies and New Day customer use.
    - Promotion: New Day film brochures, mailing list, and mailing report printout, 1988-1989 (Box 51)
    - Promotion: Reports, articles, newsletters, and correspondence, 1988-1990 (Box 51)
      Contents include a report on "Video collections and public libraries" from the American Library Association; issues of the New Day Films newsletter Inside Line, 1988-1990; articles on multicultural education, and film marketing; a group of reports on New Day promotion activities, presented at the 1990 Annual Meeting; and correspondence with the Steering Committee.
    - Promotion: Informational New Day Films brochure, 1991 (Box 51)
    - Promotion: Reports and correspondence, 1991-1993 (Box 51)
      Promotion activities reports and correspondence; issues of the New Day Films newsletter Inside Line, 1991; and a report on the NVR distribution grant.
    - Promotion: Reports and correspondence, 1991-1996 (Box 52)
      Almost all promotional reports and summaries. Includes report from Promotion Consultant with recommendations.
    - Promotion: New Day membership survey and results, 1992 (Box 52)
    - Promotion: Printed publicity for films Voices from Inside, Twitch and Shout, and Spirit of the Dawn, 1996 (Box 52)
    - Promotion: Correspondence files, 1995-1999; 6 folders (Box 52)
      Large group of correspondence files in the form of email printouts related to New Day Films promotional activities. Included are text from promotion reports, and some sets of correspondence bear color tabs with subjects.
    - Promotion: Task reports, correspondence, 1999-2000 and undated; 5 folders (Box 52)
      The first folder contains task committee reports on an end-user research project and the New Day catalog, among others. Other materials include annual marketing and promotion reports that include reports on activities such as conferences and festivals, mailings, new member recruitment, and film submissions.
    - Promotion: Correspondence files, 1999-2001; 3 folders (Box 53)
    - Shipping: Correspondence, propositions, proposals, 1986-1992; 4 folders (Box 53)
    - Tasks: Reports, assignments, meeting minutes, correspondence, 1985-1998; 7 folders (Box 53)
      As part of their responsibilities, members were assigned tasks by a coordinator, and the many emails, memos, and task reports in these files document that process. Examples of tasks include: catalog production; conference/festival guide; mailing list maintenance; internal newsletter; and annual meeting planning. Tasks were reported on annually to the membership and throughout the year to the Steering Committee.
    - Tasks: Reports, assignments, meeting minutes, correspondence, 1998-2001 and undated; 3 folders (Box 54)
    - Website: Project correspondence, report, task force, 1995-2001 and undated; 12 folders (Box 54)
      On the eve of New Day's 25th anniversary in 1996, the membership established a website for the cooperative. Materials in these files - chiefly emails - document the process from securing the domain name in December 1995 to developing the full-blown site, working with server hosts and designers, and managing it into 2001. Website committee reports are abundant, as well as printed screenshots with handwritten annotations.
- Facilitators' Chronological Files, 1983-2001; 3.0 Linear Feet 6 boxes
  This series was maintained by New Day Films consultant and facilitator Arlene Goldbard, probably for her own use. Its filing sequence has been left in its original order and its original title has been retained.
  Early materials include the first consultants' report from 1984, which outlines in detail the state of the New Day Films cooperative at the time. Also located in this series is the 181-page manual for new members. As time goes on, email printouts are the dominant format. Other materials include handwritten meeting notes; reports; memos; personnel reports and requests; and data analyses.
  Much of this material was sent to or from the facilitators in preparation for Steering Committee and Annual membership meetings. There is considerable overlap with other series in the collection, especially the Cooperative Files Meetings and Topical Files groups.
  - Phone interviews on state of cooperative, 1983 May-December (Box 55)
    Interviews were conducted with New Day Films membership.
  - Central Office report, budget, steering committee minutes, 1984 June-December (Box 55)
  - Adams & Goldbard final report, 1984 July 7 (Box 55)
    A 36-page report by consultant firm on the state of New Day Films that evaluates all aspects of its functions and recommends changes and improvements. Table of contents includes: Phase One - Phone Interviews, The Culture of New Day; The Economics of New Day; Meetings; Year-Round Governance; Policies and Practices; and Promotions. There are no annotations within. The report's blank paper covers and no official attribution or date statements seem to indicate that this is a final draft.
  - Article: Promotion as a Way of Life, The New York Review, 1984 October 11 (Box 55)
  - Centralized business coordinator logistics, Central Office information, and pre-1984 background (Box 55)
  - Notes regarding June meeting, agreements, pre-1984 background (Box 55)
  - Report of Transition Committee on Central Office, 1984 (Box 55)
  - Shares system options, 1985 January (Box 55)
  - Retreat, 1985 (Box 55)
    Materials include background history, survey results, and reports.
  - Share survey notes, 1985 (Box 55)
  - Share survey responses, 1985 (Box 55)
  - Shares, 1985 (Box 55)
  - Staffing/structure proposals, 1985 (Box 55)
  - Assorted notes from meetings, 1985-1986 (Box 55)
  - Conferences, 1985-1987 (Box 55)
    Several items, including correspondence to the membership, a promotions report which includes conference activities, and a report on conferences involving New Day members.
  - New members packet [manual], 1986 January 8 (Box 55)
    This 181-page manual for new members includes explanations and information on: first-year costs for new members; New Day budget; lease agreements; mailing lists; telemarketing; task lists; and telephone sales. Also includes sample blank forms, a list of conferences, festivals and television events for 1985-1986, the annual meeting minutes for 1985, and articles about New Day Films.
  - Art/Anthro subgroups, 1986 August-October (Box 55)
  - Articles on copyright, off-air recording, and educational use, 1986 (Box 55)
    Authors include Maryann Chach in the magazine Sightlines, and the American Library Association.
  - New Day Video Club memo with form, 1986 (Box 55)
  - New Day graphic logo creation, 1986-1987 (Box 56)
  - New Day mailing lists, 1986-1987 (Box 56)
  - Sub-groups mailing lists and correspondence, 1986-1987 (Box 56)
    Includes letter regarding the creation of a women's issues subgroup.